foreign
[Music]
typically starting about four to five
years after their last period about half
of postmenopausal women suffer what we
used to call Volvo vaginal atrophy now
referred to by the name GSM genital
urinary syndrome of menopause thanks to
the low low vaginal atrophy terminology
consensus conference who needed a more
publicly acceptable term after all the
word atrophy had negative connotations
in the word vagina is not a generally
accepted term for public discourse they
liken it to the shift from the
pejorative impotence to erectile
dysfunction whatever you call it
involves changes to the vulva the
external genitalia the vagina the birth
canal and bladder caused by menopausal
changes in hormone levels vaginal
symptoms include vaginal dryness burning
itchiness and irritation pain during
penetrative sex and post-coital bleeding
from the thinning of the vaginal lining
urinary symptoms can include recurrent
bladder infections and incontinence some
women with mild GSM remain asymptomatic
for others symptoms severity can
preclude intercourse altogether and
result in discomfort even just sitting
or wiping in a survey of thousands of
women with GSM 59 said their symptoms
considerably decrease their enjoyment of
sexual activity and 23 reported having
an adverse effect on their General
enjoyment of life
while other menopausal symptoms like hot
flashes tend to improve over time GSM
symptoms tend to get progressively worse
unfortunately women rarely seek medical
help even though they're safe and simple
treatments available the first line
treatment for mild to moderate vaginal
dryness are lubricants and moisturizer
lubricants are designed to reduce
friction during sexual activity whereas
vaginal moisturizers are used on a
regular basis daily or every two to
three days as needed to provide
day-to-day Comfort by mimicking natural
vaginal secretions regardless of sexual
activity
water-based lubricants have the
advantage of being non-staining and are
associated with fewer genital symptoms
such as discomfort or burning compared
to silicone based lubricants
what's the best vaginal moisturizer this
head-to-head study vaginal estrogen
versus replens an expensive vaginal
moisturizer claiming special bioadhesive
ingredients versus a placebo gel of
hydroxyethyl cellulose which is found in
products 15 times cheaper like KY Jelly
after 12 weeks the researchers found no
difference between any of them they all
worked the same this striking double
negative finding led to an accompanying
commentary in the American Medical
Association journal to conclude that
until there's evidence to suggest
otherwise post-menopausal women
experiencing Volvo vaginal symptoms
should choose the cheapest moisturizer
lubricant available over the counter
instead of wasting your money that was
for efficacy though what about safety
the World Health Organization recommends
based on the SMI test that personal
lubricants and vaginal moisturizers not
exceed an osmolality of 380. that's a
measure of how concentrated the
dissolved components are how did they
come up with that number by lubing up
slugs SMI stands for slug mucosal
irritation they cover slugs with
lubricant over a five-day period and
measure how much mucosal irritation and
tissue damage the slug experiences no
adverse effects below the 380 cutoff but
something like KY Jelly at over 2000
induced mild and moderate irritation and
something off the charts like afterglide
at 5000 plus cause severe irritation and
tissue damage dozens of commonly used
lubricants and moisturizers available
worldwide have been put to the test and
the only two vaginal moisturizers that
met the who criteria were the yes brand
aloe vera gel based moisturizer and the
balance active brand hyaluronic
acid-based one the only lubricants that
made the cut were those made by Brands
yes good clean love system Joe and one
product by durax they're since lube gel
but not their Playfield lubricant
foreign